<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-08-16T19:11:25-04:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Emily Tseng</title><subtitle>Emily studies computing and technology design.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Applying to the MSR PhD Fellowship</title><link href="/jekyll/update/2022/06/10/msr-phd-fellowship.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Applying to the MSR PhD Fellowship" /><published>2022-06-10T20:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-06-10T20:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/jekyll/update/2022/06/10/msr-phd-fellowship</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll/update/2022/06/10/msr-phd-fellowship.html"><![CDATA[<p>In 2021, I had the enormous honor of being selected for the Microsoft Research PhD Fellowship. Since the 2022 call was issued, I’ve received several emails from applicants asking what to do. I get it! I was there too—stunned at earning the nomination, confused about what to do next, unsure about the merit of my work, and, on top of it all, swamped in summer deadlines.</p>

<p>Here is the general advice I have been sending applicants when they reach out. I hope it helps.</p>

<p><i>Do you have any general advice for creating a successful application? What is the main challenge to keep in mind? Do you have any insight into which part of the proposal is the most important?</i>
So first, disclaimers aside, I don’t know that I have any insights on what part of the proposal made me successful. I actually still to this day don’t know who read it and why they made the final decision. But here’s how I strategized around the app this time last year.</p>

<p>(1) Find examples.</p>

<p>I approached the application like a dry run of putting together job materials for a faculty position. Several scholars in my field (HCI and information science) had just gone on the job market, so I went hunting for their research statements to get a sense of what the format tends to be. I would recommend doing this as early in the PhD as you can—it helped me sort out where in the field my work sits, and helped me get to know people to look up to.</p>

<p>There were also a couple of folks who posted their materials for PhD fellowships, specifically. <a href="https://www.morgan-klaus.com/fellowships.html">Morgan Klaus Scheuerman</a> and <a href="https://medium.com/@jazettej/7-tips-for-applying-for-the-microsoft-research-ada-lovelace-fellowship-d4a5a8910345">Jazette Johnson</a>, I owe you both!</p>

<p>(2) Write the app like a grant.</p>

<p>My advisors told me very early on to think of the application more like a grant than anything else. For me, this meant forcing focus on a subset of all the research projects I’m involved in. The fellowship doesn’t commit you to executing one project or the other, so it’s more about telling a compelling story that also shows off the work you’ve done to-date. (I do actually intend to execute parts of what I proposed in my dissertation, but I’m not committed to doing all of it).</p>

<p>I also didn’t do too much to force my research interests to fit with what anyone at MSR does. My app was much more about my group’s work and my ideas.</p>

<p>With all of that in mind—writing the application was a long process of going back and forth with advisors and trusted peers about what did and didn’t make sense, and how to refine the contribution for the right research communities. I made sure to tell my advisors early on that I would need their eyes and ears on drafts by certain dates, and got a lot of feedback from peers in related research communities. It was definitely an exhaustive process that took a significant amount of time out of my summer.</p>

<p>Happy to answer more Qs or do a 30min 1:1 via Zoom if helpful for you. Best of luck, and above all else, please know this process contains so much inherent randomness and will not reflect your worth or your quality as a scholar. The process of writing these materials was helpful for me forcing synthesis out of my research ideas, and that by itself was very worthwhile. We’re lucky in our field to have many fellowships available – I hope Google, Facebook and maybe even Intel etc are on your radar too.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In 2021, I had the enormous honor of being selected for the Microsoft Research PhD Fellowship. Since the 2022 call was issued, I’ve received several emails from applicants asking what to do. I get it! I was there too—stunned at earning the nomination, confused about what to do next, unsure about the merit of my work, and, on top of it all, swamped in summer deadlines.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="/jekyll/update/2021/04/23/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2021-04-23T15:21:10-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-23T15:21:10-04:00</updated><id>/jekyll/update/2021/04/23/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll/update/2021/04/23/welcome-to-jekyll.html"><![CDATA[<p>You’ll find this post in your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_posts</code> directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jekyll serve</code>, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</p>

<p>Jekyll requires blog post files to be named according to the following format:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YEAR-MONTH-DAY-title.MARKUP</code></p>

<p>Where <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YEAR</code> is a four-digit number, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MONTH</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">DAY</code> are both two-digit numbers, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MARKUP</code> is the file extension representing the format used in the file. After that, include the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.</p>

<p>Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">print_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">name</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">"Hi, </span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="nb">name</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">"</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
<span class="n">print_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'Tom'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="c1">#=&gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Check out the <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home">Jekyll docs</a> for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at <a href="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll’s GitHub repo</a>. If you have questions, you can ask them on <a href="https://talk.jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll Talk</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.]]></summary></entry></feed>